<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: psychology | Josh Bavari's Thoughts]]></title>
  <link href="http://jbavari.github.io/blog/categories/psychology/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jbavari.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2020-01-10T07:41:03-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://jbavari.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Josh Bavari]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[jbavari@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Take Action Now]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbavari.github.io/blog/2019/12/23/take-action-now/"/>
    <updated>2019-12-23T20:52:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbavari.github.io/blog/2019/12/23/take-action-now</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I feel that there is a lot of things I can say about the world today. First, there is a lot of bullcrap that we churn through in our minds. You know the sort that I&rsquo;m talking about &ndash; the self deception. The thought that I&rsquo;m going places, without taking the action to take those steps to start that path. Those new years resolutions. Those goals that you write down, but do not get action items defined and set up on the calendar. Those same action items you don&rsquo;t check in on from time to time. Things that we tell ourselves that we&rsquo;ll get to tomorrow. We rarely do. We think in terms of intentions &ndash; and judging ourselves retroactively based on those intentions rather than the actions.</p>

<p>Our actions become who we are. This much is true by everyone. Most people carry a picture of themselves in their mind that they think they are. In those that really are that person of action, rarely spend time thinking of what they should be doing. They are currently working towards being what they should be, instead of thinking of it. &ldquo;A good plan, violently executed now, is better than a perfect plan next week.&rdquo; &ndash; George Patton.</p>

<p>They used to call George Patton &ndash; old blood and guts. Here&rsquo;s his thoughts on embracing your part to play, regardless of the role:</p>

<p>&ldquo;All of the real heroes are not storybook combat fighters, either. Every single man in this Army plays a vital role &hellip; . Don’t ever think that your job is unimportant. Every man has a job to do and he must do it. Every man is a vital link in the great chain.&rdquo;</p>

<p>This same mindset exists in today&rsquo;s day and age. We all have a crucial role to play in the world of hate. We must lay steadfast in our power in the world. Strive the be the best at what you do. We all pay our part back to mankind. When we embrace what our purpose is &ndash; and strive to better in that department &ndash; we make the world a better place.</p>

<p>When you find yourself becoming paralyzed by needing a perfect plan, remember: you came here to serve, to take action, to think through a plan, and to execute. Don&rsquo;t get hung up on the plan phase too long or you won&rsquo;t get to play your part. Only your actions echo through time.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a trick to take action sooner &ndash; if you&rsquo;re starting a new project or path, think of a few things that you have done already towards that goal.</p>

<p>For example, when setting a weight loss goal: &ldquo;I want to get down to 185&rdquo;. You could tell yourself, &ldquo;I&rsquo;m at 205, down from 220. I&rsquo;m already down 20%&rdquo;.</p>

<p>Citing some psychology tricks I&rsquo;ve pulled from the book, &ldquo;Switch: How to change things when change is hard&rdquo;. This book tells a story about sales tactics &ndash; one store gives customers a &lsquo;buy 8, get one free card&rsquo;. Another store gives customers &lsquo;buy 10, get one free&rsquo;, but they give the first 2 items starting off the bat. The second store sees an 80% return in customers. The psychology here is, they&rsquo;ve gotten started, the momentum is there.</p>

<p>Remember, physics always wins. Momentum exists in our mind, overcome that by using the gravity of starting conditions to help it along.</p>

<p>Keep a calendar to keep momentum going. Put an &lsquo;X&rsquo; on the date to remind yourself of the building momentum. Once it starts, it will be harder to stop.</p>

<p>Take action now. Get started. That starting momentum can carry you along.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
