<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: development | Josh Bavari's Thoughts]]></title>
  <link href="http://jbavari.github.io/blog/categories/development/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jbavari.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2020-01-10T19:05:15-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://jbavari.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Josh Bavari]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[jbavari@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Knowledge consumption routine]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbavari.github.io/blog/2020/01/02/knowledge-consumption-routine/"/>
    <updated>2020-01-02T17:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbavari.github.io/blog/2020/01/02/knowledge-consumption-routine</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I love having conversations with other people about reading. Topics in the realm of what they read, why they read, how much they read, where they read, and the habits of how they read. The amount of choices available to any person at any time are at an all time high and ever rising.</p>

<p>Knowledge itself is an enormous black hole &ndash; not in the sense that it&rsquo;s pulling everything in to it, but that it&rsquo;s ever growing and potentially endless. The amount of words written is expanding universal levels! OK, I&rsquo;m getting way off topic of the point of this post. But.. Try and think for a second that everything that has been written by humans in their lifetime, some captured, some lost in time. The sheer amount of numbers is exponential.</p>

<p>That being said, I&rsquo;ve recently taken the <a href="https://www.goodlifeproject.com/sparketypes/">Sparketypes quiz</a> from Jonathan Fields (came across while reading the book Start Finishing). Turns out, I&rsquo;m a Maven and a Sage. Which for those unaware, a Maven is someone who loves learning for learning sake and a Sage is one who enjoys sharing and teaching others things.</p>

<p>So if all that there is to know is a black hole, I&rsquo;m an scientist flying through space attempting to observe and learn it all while radioing back home the messages.</p>

<p>Anyways&hellip;</p>

<p>I wish I could find some way to calculate the amount of hours I consume reading on the internet, books, kindle, as well as audio based content.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m going to try and outline my reading habits in this quick little post in an attempt to shed some new ideas for others looking for a good reading routine.</p>

<p>I read and consume many bits of information:</p>

<ul>
<li>Daily email newsletters</li>
<li>Internet blogs and articles</li>
<li>Physical books</li>
<li>Audible</li>
<li>E-books on my Kindle</li>
</ul>


<p>Additionally, I have some habits in my reading that others have asked me about. I honestly cannot remember where I learned the habit of reading whenever I can. I think it was Bill Gates or someone who said they read when they&rsquo;re in line, when they&rsquo;re waiting for someone to meet up with, etc etc. That&rsquo;s exactly the approach I go for. I try and read during:</p>

<ul>
<li>The morning rise</li>
<li>The daily walk(s)</li>
<li>Throughout the day</li>
<li>Wrapping up the night</li>
<li>While I&rsquo;m driving (audiobooks)</li>
<li>When I&rsquo;m waiting for a friend to arrive, using my Kindle app</li>
<li>Sometimes during lunch (I keep my kindle with me at most times)</li>
<li>While I&rsquo;m out for lunch or dinner</li>
<li>Literally any chance I can get when my brain is enaged</li>
</ul>


<p>Now, I&rsquo;ll try to outline my consumption of these mediums and habits!</p>

<h1>The content mediums</h1>

<h2>Regularly Occurring Email Newsletters</h2>

<p>I subscribe to a lot of interesting fellows in the psychology, self help, and other various &lsquo;self-improvement&rsquo; email newsletters. I really enjoy some of their articles as brainstorming seeds and kicking off discovery of new ideas. I&rsquo;ll estimate I spend anywhere from 5-10 minutes on either the post itself or links to other articles on the website.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://seths.blog/subscribe/">Seth Godin</a> &ndash; varies in length, great thoughts about anything in marketing, sales, psychology, and all around thought provoking material.</li>
<li><a href="https://dailystoic.com/new-start-here/">The Daily Stoic</a> &ndash; daily writings of the stoicism philosophy, from Ryan Holiday&rsquo;s interpretations.</li>
<li><a href="https://ryanholiday.net/reading-newsletter/">Ryan Holiday&rsquo;s newsletter</a> &ndash; book recommendations from Ryan Holiday himself.</li>
<li><a href="https://markmanson.net/newsletter">Mark Manson (Mondays)</a> &ndash; spitballed content from Mark Manson&rsquo;s email.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.nirandfar.com/subscribe/">Nir Eyal</a> &ndash; behavioral design newletter.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.danpink.com/ac/latest-newsletter/">Daniel Pink</a> &ndash; author of Drive, A Whole New Mind, and more &ndash; weekly content.</li>
<li><a href="https://qbq.com">QBQ</a> &ndash; from the author John G Miller, ideas about accountability.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Internet blogs and articles</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;d say I spend about 5-20 minutes sometimes longer, varying from available article content and the interest of content to me.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com">Hacker News</a> posts &ndash; any that tickle my brain (it&rsquo;s a lot)</li>
<li>Related professional topics in my work hours (software related, leadership articles, system design, etc)</li>
</ul>


<h2>Physical books</h2>

<p>At anytime, I have a stack of about 2-3 books that I want to read. I get these from many sources, and right now, there is no rhyme or reason to my choosing of a physical book over an e-book.</p>

<p>How I choose the books is still a mystery to me. At the time of writing this, I have a few piled up on my bookshelf ready to be read; my queue consists of: Black Box Thinking, The Black Swan, Getting to Yes, and Aware.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll usually ask for books for any gifts any want to give me as a go-to when someone asks what I&rsquo;d like.</p>

<h2>Audible</h2>

<p>I walk my dog every morning. This time on the walk is some prime time for mindfulness as well as listening to some quality audiobook content. I&rsquo;m a huge audible fan.</p>

<p>I love having some positive thoughts shared on my walk. As of late, it&rsquo;s been focused on leadership, mindfulness, and philosophy. Nothing better than getting a day started with some positive thoughts filling up your subconscious, as our minds tend to absorb whatever is in the community consciousness. At the time of writing this, i&rsquo;ve been listening to Stillness is the Key and The Art of Power.</p>

<h2>E-books on my kindle</h2>

<p>I just got a Kindle paperwhite as an upgrade from my very old Kindle 3rd Edition (the one with the keyboard). While at first skeptical, I&rsquo;m now in love with my paperwhite. Not only does it have a nice back light &ndash; but it&rsquo;s super portable to take in my back pocket to sneak out over lunch or when I get a free moment. I also have the app on my phone, which let&rsquo;s me read when I&rsquo;m in a waiting scenario, like at the doctors office, waiting in line, etc etc. I try to sneak as much reading on the go with my kindle, as well as when I&rsquo;m stationary at home.</p>

<h1>My reading routine</h1>

<h2>The morning rise</h2>

<p>First off, I&rsquo;ve moved my cell phone away from my bed side stand. I&rsquo;ve replaced it with my old Kindle (3rd edition). This small habit change has me grabbing for my old kindle rather than diving into whatever my smart phone demands of me. This small trick instantly gets me in the mindset to read first.</p>

<p>I wake up and read the Seth Godin post first. I love that these daily emails provide insight into common day sales and marketing strategy and tactics. Additionally, I love that Seth Godin thinks of the human in us and aims to appeal to that side of us.</p>

<p>I then read the Daily Stoic post from Ryan Holiday. I love the constant reminder that we&rsquo;re human, our time on this earth is temporary, and we will need to be kind to all. That and I&rsquo;m a sucker for the stoicism philosophy in any form.</p>

<p>Finally, I go to my comfy recliner chair and read either my kindle or a book, whichever I&rsquo;m into (Currently: &ldquo;Start Finishing&rdquo; on Kindle and &ldquo;Black Box Thinking&rdquo; in book form).</p>

<p>From here, I at get at least 15-30 minutes of reading time, pending more if I&rsquo;m super interested in the book.</p>

<h2>The daily walk(s)</h2>

<p>Once the clock finally hits 8:30 AM or so, my little dog Amaya demands a walk. Great! Now I get some time to listen to my audio book while we go on our daily 1.5 mile walk. Sometimes more, sometimes less. Regardless, this gets me about 10 hours of listening a month. Audible also gives some other fun stats for listening &ndash; my minimum listening time was in November of this year, at 5h 52m. My maximum, oddly enough not due to the weather, is December with 20h 48m!</p>

<h2>Throughout the day</h2>

<p>While the day rolls along, I try to sneak in some reading time anyway I can. I might bust out my kindle over lunch while I&rsquo;m at work. I might read a few internet articles / blogs / or whatever else I might find interesting throughout the day.</p>

<p>While I&rsquo;m at work, I try to look up blog posts that are relevant either to leadership, management, programming, communication, or any other issue I am currently working through during my very dynamic days.</p>

<h2>Wrapping up the night</h2>

<p>Now that I&rsquo;ve got my kindle next to my bedside stand &ndash; I try to grab a few minutes of reading while I&rsquo;m jumping into bed. This small hack of removing my phone has given me one option &ndash; the kindle. I already struggle with insomnia and I&rsquo;m finding that having the kindle there helps me read a bit and unwind. By this point, I need something to stop the constant sensory overload that the smart phone provides.</p>

<p>I might grab anywhere from 15-30 minutes at my night time reading routine.</p>

<h2>Putting it all in perspective</h2>

<p>Again, these numbers are mainly hail mary estimates.</p>

<p>Morning: 15m-30m (daily newsletter) + 30m-1h (book reading) + 50m (audible) = 1h 30m &ndash; 2h 20m</p>

<p>Day: 15m &ndash; 1h</p>

<p>Night: 15m &ndash; 30m</p>

<p>Coming to a guessed grand total for a minimum of 2 hours to a maximum of 3 hours and 50 minutes.</p>

<p>For just a small time investment, I can steal quite a good chunk of learning time. Since I&rsquo;m being sucked into the knowledge black hole, I tend to lose track of times in my small reading habits. That&rsquo;s OK by me though, since the constant reading habits help enforce knowledge retention since many books seem to cover similiar material, thus being stored to my long term storage!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why I read]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbavari.github.io/blog/2019/12/29/why-i-read/"/>
    <updated>2019-12-29T17:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbavari.github.io/blog/2019/12/29/why-i-read</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Let me ask you a quick question: if you know that reading is essential to certain parts of learning and growth, then you already know why you read, but is it deeper than that? Is it something engrained in our subconscious minds through hundreds if not thousands of years of evolution?</p>

<p>In today&rsquo;s current society, the internet has enabled an entire species to read and listen on a global scale. Reading and listening is the de facto mechanism in which to share human knowledge to many generations past. There are endless amounts of digital content one can get through the medium of the internet. (I try and <a href="/blog/2020/01/02/knowledge-consumption-routine/">dive into that here</a>)</p>

<p>NOTE: I&rsquo;m going to bucket the &lsquo;watch&rsquo; category into listen and/or read. People read tons of online junk anyway!</p>

<p>We know it in old caves as wall carvings and paintings. There is the knowledge those cavemen passed along to their tribe. The unfortunate thing about that was that only those who veered onto the wall could read the message. The other issue would be &ndash; whose cave was this, anyway?! (and what are these large dinosaurs?!) These messages might be wrong or have a different method of thinking than we currently do now. There&rsquo;s no way to remediate the differences, since the author may not always be available for discussion.</p>

<p>The internet, in some sense, eased this burden by providing an infinite level of walls that tribes could erect mass cave paintings in the endless amount of caves.</p>

<p>However, the internet has also enabled another mystery to the human mind: the paradox of choice. How does one today pick what to absorb next? in the millions of physical books, digitial e-books (and scanned copies of ancients), audio books, journals, online journals, blogs, and the bucket category of &lsquo;web pages&rsquo; out in the world?</p>

<blockquote><p>“Learning to choose is hard. Learning to choose well is harder. And learning to choose well in a world of unlimited possibilities is harder still, perhaps too hard.” ― Barry Schwartz, The Paradox of Choice: Why More Is Less</p></blockquote>

<p>Capturing the knowledge itself once found is a near impossible task, I&rsquo;m not going to even touch on that topic because it&rsquo;s thoroughly argued over enough on Hacker news. I&rsquo;m going to attempt to share how I got to my filter to make reading an absolute enjoyable part of my life. Hop on over to my <a href="/knowledge">knowledge</a> page, as I try to capture my knowledge sources there.</p>

<p>What isn&rsquo;t clear to me as of late is &lsquo;why&rsquo; I read what I read. I&rsquo;m attempting to write this post to enlighten myself and others about this filter that occurs when I move on to my next book.</p>

<h1>My Caves</h1>

<p>The caves I absorb from now come from a variety of sources:</p>

<ul>
<li>Email newsletters</li>
<li>Audible content</li>
<li>Kindle / E-books</li>
<li>Physical Books</li>
</ul>


<p>Let&rsquo;s dive into how I select each of these.</p>

<h2>My filtering pattern</h2>

<p>For the 2019 year, I wanted to aim for reading two books a month aimed at two topics: personal growth and professional acumen growth. Sometimes, the books would be both. Other times, it would be totally random. It just so happens that what I read for joy is also in lined with what I love: psychology &ndash; how the human mind works.</p>

<p>I chose these two topics because they are areas that I would like to strengthen a bit more.</p>

<p>When it comes to choosing email newsletters, I may easily follow the newsletters of authors that I&rsquo;ve enjoyed reading their books. The first that come to mind are Seth Godin, Nir Eyal, Daniel Pink, and Ryan Holiday. Many of these authors share a common stereotype &ndash; sales, marketing, psychology, and connection with vulnerability.</p>

<p>I often joke that if I didn&rsquo;t go the computer science route, I would have gone to neuroscience or psychology. I&rsquo;m a hobbyist psychologist, with no patients who need my help.</p>

<p>Certainly hitting the ripe age of 35 has triggered me to think more about philosophy, the meaning of the world, the strive to end or defer suffering, and the ability to see the world anew.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve driven into professional development &ndash; being a manager for the last year or so has given me a &lsquo;eyes wide open&rsquo; view to the world of management. Most of my reading has been more than management though &ndash; it&rsquo;s more on leadership. However, I know and understand that <a href="https://qbq.com/leadership-management/">the best managers are the best leaders</a>.</p>

<p>When I go to pick the next book, I apply the following pattern:</p>

<ul>
<li>Look for the latest area of researchers in the domain.</li>
<li>Look for the oldest area of researchers in the domain.</li>
<li>Look at any book references that came about in the last book I read. (Many times the references are where the author pulled some of her knowledge from, so that&rsquo;s another great source.)</li>
<li>I keep a rolling list of reads that may be interesting &ndash; either from emails, books references from TED or Ignite talks, and more.</li>
</ul>


<p>Some examples of this pattern:</p>

<p>&ldquo;Well Geez, Josh. I seem to be ultra distracted lately and not being able to finish anything. What does the research say on this?&rdquo;</p>

<blockquote><p>I then look up books in the focus domain. I find a few: Indistractable, Get out of your own way, The art of communicating, The art of thinking clearly, The Organized Mind, and Atomic Habits. These all seem like good reads. What knowledge sources did these authors pull from? Are there any TED talks about this? Do these speakers have any references or leads they throw out in the talk? What about friends recommmendations? Who is the most focused person I know? What suggestions do they have on the topic, or leads, or books, etc?</p></blockquote>

<p>Certainly there is more to the pattern than what I posted above, but that&rsquo;s my first stab at trying to understand my pattern.</p>

<p>Once I&rsquo;ve decided what to read, I then decide on the medium.</p>

<h2>Audible vs reading</h2>

<p>When I choose a book, I think of which medium will be best to absorb it. Mainly I turn to kindle these days, because it can go with me everywhere. If a subject is interesting enough that I want to absorb it throughout the day, then Kindle is the de facto choice.</p>

<p>However, sometimes I will choose audible over reading because I want to absorb it while I&rsquo;m walking, driving, or have some free time doing chores around the house.</p>

<p>The key here is &ndash; can I absorb this content while using my hands &ndash; or do I want to absorb it fully? When it comes to physical vs kindle, I mainly go kindle due to the accessibility. However, if someone is asking me for a gift, I ask for physical!</p>

<h1>But, why?</h1>

<p>Why such the obsession with the human mind? In this world of a growing number of human mind and intelligence, I want to know what drives people. Certainly, there is the book <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Drive-Surprising-Truth-About-Motivates/dp/1594484805">Drive</a>, but I&rsquo;m not concerned with the drive that people have in the competitive world of business. But rather, why do people do what they do? What is the engine in their minds and hearts and what fuel is driving it?</p>

<p>Recently, I took one of the many online quizes and learning that I&rsquo;m a Maven type. This seemed to align with my intuition, which makes a ton of sense to my obsessions with learning for learning sake.</p>

<p>But still.. What am I looking to learn? I lean an ear towards psychology, philosophy, science, and technology. Why?</p>

<p>If I had another life to live (which I know is not reality), I would spend that life hopefully learning all the things I didn&rsquo;t learn the first time around.</p>

<p>If I absolutely had to put a reasoning to my thirst for knowledge, it would be this:</p>

<p>I have a deep joy of learning. It&rsquo;s the true lesson that I learned from college. (Paul Graham <a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/lesson.html">also wrote an essay on this</a>). I have a deep fear about not knowing. I&rsquo;m not content with the &lsquo;it is what it is&rsquo; phrase. In the last year though, I&rsquo;ve tried to change that phrase to be &lsquo;I accept it for how it is&rsquo; &ndash; but not until learning why. Once I can learn every 1% of the why, I am more willing to accept the why.</p>

<p>Yet, I&rsquo;ve still not found the answer to what lies in the heart of man to drive the decisions he makes. Maslow&rsquo;s hierarchy of needs surely comes close to these ideals, but are those same motiviations still in tact today the same as when Maslow thought up the idea in 1943?</p>

<p>Certainly most parts of this world still seek the bottom layers of Maslow&rsquo;s needs, but what about the higher levels today in the first world?</p>

<p>Maybe I&rsquo;ll never learn why I read what I read. Certainly writing this post hasn&rsquo;t lead me any closer to understand my own drive, so what chance do I have in getting closer to understanding others? I guess I will have to accept that asking one person and their answer must suffice.</p>

<p>The last bit I will sketch out is that in today&rsquo;s day and age, we know and understand that the subconscious mind drives us &ndash; like the rider on the elephant, it goes where it will go no matter the tugging and please from the riders. Even asking someone their drives will still not reveal their elephants desires, because they themselves do not know it.</p>

<h1>Closing notes</h1>

<p>As per the book, Psycho Cybernetics, it is our own self-image that we seek to align with our actions. Perhaps my self-image is one that I am a seeker of knowledge, no matter the effort or cost. Surely, the Sparketypes quiz I took that states I&rsquo;m a maven lines up with that self-image. Even if the quiz was a placebo to enhance this self-image, I&rsquo;m taking it.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll continue to read to absorb as much knowledge as I can, and attempt to write as much as I can to help share this knowledge. All for the sake of knowledge.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Clean Architecture - Book Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbavari.github.io/blog/2019/10/08/clean-architecture-book-review/"/>
    <updated>2019-10-08T21:48:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbavari.github.io/blog/2019/10/08/clean-architecture-book-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve recently read and held a nerd book club at work regarding Clean Architecture. Overall, I found this read easy to grok and entertain a few new ideas about software development. Uncle Bob also had a few things <a href="https://blog.cleancoder.com/uncle-bob/2012/08/13/the-clean-architecture.html">on his blog post</a> about this topic.</p>

<p>If I could wrap up one picture that encompases the book:</p>

<p><img src="https://blog.cleancoder.com/uncle-bob/images/2012-08-13-the-clean-architecture/CleanArchitecture.jpg" alt="This image" /></p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve also recently read parts of Domain Driven Design that introduce this same concept. I think Uncle Bob does a great job of sharing some great examples of the book of how architecture is an art, one that can morph with the needs of the project at hand, and is subject to trade-offs through the entire lifecycle of software. I love that the book starts off expressing the idea that thinking of delivery early on is a wise decision to incorporate into the architecture design.</p>

<p>Some other great points I found worthy of mention:</p>

<ul>
<li>How to think of the division of software with regards to firmware and hardware abstraction layers.</li>
<li>Most things are details &ndash; the framework, the database, the GUI, firmware &ndash; keep it separated from the internal domain layers of your business logic however possible.</li>
<li>SOLID Principles are important &ndash; also integrate into architecture design.</li>
<li>Architecture design with traditional monolith, service oriented, and micro-service anti-pattern warnings.</li>
<li>The idea that there is no silver bullet &ndash; <a href="https://twitter.com/codepitbull/status/784691906005635072">A good developer is like a werewolf: afraid of silver bullets</a></li>
</ul>


<p>This book club also gave the team some time to reflect and dive into the design of our current projects. Overall, this was a great book for a team to cover and come up with some action items to drive better software going forward.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Respect yourself]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbavari.github.io/blog/2015/11/27/respect-yourself/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-27T21:58:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbavari.github.io/blog/2015/11/27/respect-yourself</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m writing this post as a memoir for myself, a retrospect of sorts. I read <a href="http://sethgodin.typepad.com/seths_blog/2015/11/unconscious-consumption.html">Seth Godins blog about Unconscious consumption</a> and that post inspired me to write this post.</p>

<p>In the last 3 years, amazing events have unfolded. I helped create a start up, <a href="http://raisemore.com">RaiseMore</a>. I moved to Boulder, Colorado. I got a job at Ionic. I met a strong, amazing, beautiful woman who is my girlfriend.</p>

<p>I trained jiu-jitsu 4-5 times a week, I kept working on my strength, and trying to inspire others to do the same. I was striving to always read self-help books, watching informational videos, TED talks, ignite talks, challenging and pushing myself, and helping others grow.</p>

<p>All these new and exciting things kept happening to me. Many times before, I&rsquo;ve asked myself, &lsquo;how did I get so lucky?&rsquo;. Things just had a snowball effect and kept getting better and better!</p>

<p>I&rsquo;d like to think what attracted all these amazing things into my life was from these advancements.</p>

<p>However, something happened during these last 4 months that really threw me in a rut. I developed a poor attitude. I started thinking I was a victim. I no longer work for the company that I had looked up to for so long.</p>

<p>As I sit here now and reflect on the last few months, I know I&rsquo;ve made my fair share of mistakes. I take full responsibility for that. And due to some of those mistakes, I&rsquo;m unemployed (and looking for opportunities!) and I know it&rsquo;s my own fault.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;d like to stop and take a minute to deep dive and retrospect on what happened. I know, deep in my heart, that it all changed when <em>I stopped respecting myself and making my personal growth a priority</em>.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m realizing that while all these good things were occurring, one thing remained constant &ndash; <em>I put myself and my personal growth first</em>.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;d like to deep dive into what really happened, and discover the why.</p>

<h2>Deep diving</h2>

<p>Questions to ask:</p>

<ul>
<li>What did you do right?</li>
<li>What did you do wrong?</li>
<li>What can you do better?</li>
</ul>


<h3>What did I do right?</h3>

<p>In January, I was jumping head first into the Ionic CLI. I was familiar with Node.js, but wasn&rsquo;t nearly at the level I wanted to be at. So I jumped head first into blogs, training courses, books, and more.</p>

<p>I learned a ton by failing forward, bouncing ideas off of others, and most importantly, <em>maintaining a healthy work life balance</em>.</p>

<p>In March, I came up with the crazy idea to make the Ionic CLI easier to consume by almost any user by just point/clicking. In my free time after working on the Ionic CLI, I started cranking out <a href="http://lab.ionic.io">Ionic Lab</a> &ndash; that would do just that.</p>

<p>It was so freeing to use my creative side and use my intuition, listening to myself as I craved to learn more about Node.js and <a href="http://electron.github.io">Electron</a>!</p>

<p>After demoing Ionic Lab to the Ionic team, they were convinced this was a tool that could open the door to more developers and really improve the tooling. Thus, I was instructed to work on it full time. Such a joy!</p>

<p>Then it hit, this thing had to ship. I had to really buckle down and work out the final kinks in integrating Cordova fully into Ionic Lab, which took me down rabbit holes into discovering more about Electron than I wanted to know, fixing stdio errors and things that occurred deep in Cordova library code.</p>

<p>Once we shipped out Ionic Lab in July, I was told to focus on Ionic 2. The rest of the team had been heads down working on the codebase since March, I was the new guy, so I had to really step it up and put in the time to learn Angular 2, TypeScript, ES6, Webpack, and all the other new ground to cover.</p>

<p>It was exciting once again to jump head first into learning and exploration. But something happened that I did not expect.. I became a cynic.</p>

<h4>What did I do wrong?</h4>

<p>I think it wasn&rsquo;t until after July that things started to slow down and my personal happiness started to decline. I started working more hours (60 hours was the minimum). I stayed up late working most every night. I slept less. I started working out less (I gained 10-20 lbs). I started putting myself <em>and my personal growth</em> last.</p>

<p>I stopped calling my friends. I stopped reaching out to my support group as much. I wasn&rsquo;t maintaining my happy upbeat attitude I&rsquo;ve been told has been so inspiring.</p>

<p>I started putting work first. I started accepting others views of myself. I stopped valuing my work, my time, and my efforts to put that towards a company that at the end of the day, only wanted more and more. We all know what this leads to, <em>burn out</em>.</p>

<p>This all was boiling down to the AngularConnect conference, where we planned to unveil Ionic 2 to the European crowds. I was given a hefty task of learning all that was Ionic 2, adding cross platform functionality in Ionic 2, adjusting the Ionic CLI for v2, helping curate content for a workshop at the conference, as well as building the first Ionic v2 app, <a href="http://github.com/driftyco/ionic-conference-app">the Ionic conference app</a>.</p>

<p>All this was going down and other life issues arise, as they do. My older (15y old) dog was getting worse by the day. My girlfriend was not happy that I was putting her second to work. My friends stopped calling me. My shoulder got injured. I lost confidence in my work because I was burning out.</p>

<p>Then, a personal goal I had set didn&rsquo;t get delivered to a group of users I was really wanted to, the Windows Ionic CLI users.</p>

<p>This hurt. Failure when placed heavy, can hurt. It hurt even more when I was putting work first, and myself last.</p>

<p>Looking more hopefully at the situation..</p>

<h4>What can I do better?</h4>

<p>First off &ndash; be honest with myself. Tell others I need a helping hand when needed. Going forward, I will look out for myself better (we all know employers want employees that can look out for themselves).</p>

<p>Don&rsquo;t accept others views of myself unless I first believe them!</p>

<p>Most importantly, respecting myself. I should always take the time to have a 1 on 1 with myself and really get a sense of where I&rsquo;m at. If I need a break, use that vacation that we are so lucky to have!</p>

<p>We tend to forget that if we dont build ourselves up, the world surely wont. (Unless you are lucky enough to have awesome friends that stick through it thick and thin). Burnout happens when you don&rsquo;t let your support structure help put out of the flame before you become a pile of ash.</p>

<p>So please, take this time to evaluate yourself and your needs. Be honest with yourself. Focus on caring for yourself. Be compassionate to yourself. Let yourself make mistakes, but learn from them.</p>

<p>Focus on the positive. Surround yourself with upbeat people, ditch the negativity, and remind yourself that your future is in your hands. Take it.</p>

<p>Don&rsquo;t forget that the only difference between a victor and a victim, is their mindset.</p>

<p>Remember, there is no luck, only the work you put in and the effect you see afterwards.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Its not the tools - its you]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbavari.github.io/blog/2014/03/01/its-not-the-tools-its-you/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-01T02:16:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbavari.github.io/blog/2014/03/01/its-not-the-tools-its-you</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1>Reminder &ndash; you write the code, not the tools</h1>

<p>Duh, right?</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s a lot of debate I see about people saying you have to use a certain language or tool
to write good software or create apps. This is simply not the fact.</p>

<p>Case and point &ndash; if you write an app in iOS and it works great, the user simply does not care if it
was written in Objective-C, PhoneGap, or some other hybrid tool. (NOTE: unless the user is a troll)</p>

<p>I personally do a lot of work lately with Cordova/PhoneGap. I actively contribute to Cordova as well.
When I hear purists come down on the technology, I really wonder why.</p>

<p>Certainly, there can be some bad apps created with it. The same can be said for Objective-C!
Whatever the tool/language is, it can always be used in the wrong or inefficient way.</p>

<p>The truth is, there are some awesome technologies coming out from all kinds of directions.
What makes the tech better? The tools/languages/software used, or the overall look/feel/usage?</p>

<h2>Why am I writing this?</h2>

<p>Lately, I&rsquo;ve been trying to grow as a developer and really fine tune my craft.
I&rsquo;m writing this to remind myself &amp; hopefully remind others, any products/apps we make are only as good as we can make them.
<strong>NOT</strong> the tools we use to make them. (NOTE: sometimes a tool can improve performance, or some other aspect, but its still up to you to learn and adapt)</p>

<h2>If your app/product sucks, its your fault</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s right &ndash; true responsibility.</p>

<p>Think about this &ndash; these days developers can make awesome, usable softare with only a text editor and some command line tools.</p>

<p>Now, given some additional IDEs, SDKs, Frameworks, ETC., the same developer could make more software, generally quicker.
Was it the tools that made the finalized product awesome?</p>

<p>That being said, if you are using a tool/system/framework, and it truly does suck &ndash; guess what?
You are free to change it!</p>

<h2>The weakness is you</h2>

<p>What makes someone great at anything is when they know what they are weak at and actively improve on those weaknesses.</p>

<p>One thing I wanted to focus fire this year was hitting my weak points.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s always difficult to take a true honest look at yourself and evaluate what actions you should take. However, if you really want to improve and get ahead, there&rsquo;s no other way.</p>

<h3>Some of my weaknesses</h3>

<ul>
<li>Writing tests for my code &amp; taking a TDD approach</li>
<li>Actively testing my product (thoroughly)</li>
<li>Reading and keeping up to date with knowledge (blogs/books/etc)</li>
<li>Communicating and expressing my ideas</li>
</ul>


<h3>What I&rsquo;m trying</h3>

<ul>
<li>Expecting small improvements.</li>
<li>Iterate quickly.</li>
<li>Evaluate often.</li>
<li>Always be learning.</li>
</ul>


<h3>What I&rsquo;m doing</h3>

<ul>
<li>Starting to write tests for older code &amp; refactoring when needed, especially in Javascript &amp; Ruby</li>
<li>Getting together active test runners for iOS, Android, and the Web (CasperJS).</li>
<li>Evaluating weekly my tests I&rsquo;m writing &ndash; Using <a href="http://codeclimate.com">Code climate</a> to evaluate the quality/complexity of our code</li>
<li>Looking at other open source projects and how they write tests</li>
<li>Reading some BDD/TDD books to learn</li>
</ul>


<h2>The big picture</h2>

<p>Next time you are getting frustrated with your tools, programming language, etc &ndash; remember, it&rsquo;s up to you to improve it, or improve yourself. Cheers.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
