<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: iphone | Josh Bavari's Thoughts]]></title>
  <link href="http://jbavari.github.io/blog/categories/iphone/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jbavari.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2019-12-12T21:16:47-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://jbavari.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Josh Bavari]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[jbavari@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cordova and the Safari Web Inspector]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbavari.github.io/blog/2014/06/18/cordova-and-the-safari-web-inspector/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-18T00:22:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbavari.github.io/blog/2014/06/18/cordova-and-the-safari-web-inspector</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you&rsquo;ve ever been doing some iOS development in Cordova, you may have used the Safari Web Inspector (SWI) once or twice. You&rsquo;ve also noticed that SWI closes when the app is put in the background or you switch apps.</p>

<p>I found a sweet hack that allows you to keep your safari web inspector running regardless of whether or not the app is in the foreground or not. I&rsquo;d like to outline that in this post.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m not sure how I stumbled across this sweet hack, but I have to write it down before I forget how it&rsquo;s done. My system specs at the time of writing this is Mac OSX 10.8.5 (Mountain Lion).</p>

<h2>Whats involved</h2>

<ul>
<li>Using a simulator or connected device</li>
<li>Having Safari web inspector (SWI) running</li>
</ul>


<p>What normally happens is, when the app closes, SWI will also close. When you relaunch the app, you will need to put Safari in the foreground, click <code>Develop</code> on the menu bar, then hover <code>iPhone Simulator</code> or <code>iPhone</code>, then click the <code>index.html</code> (or your page) to connect &amp; launch SWI.</p>

<p>This is very frustrating because on the app relaunching you may have a callback happening or other code you want to debug/inspect/log on app start up. This hack lets you keep SWI and running gracefully.</p>

<p>Bare with me now, we&rsquo;re going to get funky.</p>

<h2>Setting up a global hotkey</h2>

<p>The first thing to do is to set a <a href="http://support.apple.com/kb/ph6889">global hotkey</a> &ndash; steps:</p>

<ul>
<li>Open System Preferences / Keyboard</li>
<li>On the right panel, select <code>Application Shortcuts</code></li>
<li>Add a hot key &ndash; use whatever keys you want (I used <code>CMD + ALT + I</code>)</li>
<li>Have the matching key be <code>index.html</code> or whatever your cordova&rsquo;s main html file is</li>
</ul>


<h2>Steps to keep open SWI</h2>

<ul>
<li>Launch Cordova App</li>
<li>Open SWI</li>
<li>Close SWI</li>
<li>Launch SWI with quick key as set up in global hotkey <code>Application Shortcuts</code></li>
<li>Close App</li>
<li>Reopen app &ndash; notice SWI is still running and continues to give us logging/debugging!</li>
</ul>


<p>Enjoy, friends!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
