<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: planning | Josh Bavari's Thoughts]]></title>
  <link href="http://jbavari.github.io/blog/categories/planning/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jbavari.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2020-01-10T18:50:43-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://jbavari.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Josh Bavari]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[jbavari@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2020 Goals and Systems]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbavari.github.io/blog/2020/01/04/2020-goals-and-systems/"/>
    <updated>2020-01-04T21:17:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbavari.github.io/blog/2020/01/04/2020-goals-and-systems</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After doing a <a href="/blog/2020/01/01/2019-retrospective/">2019 in review</a>, I wanted to set up some new routines for some extra discipline in my life for 2020.</p>

<p>Some systems that I want to set up:</p>

<ul>
<li>Reading more.</li>
<li>Writing more.</li>
<li>Practicing mindfulness to achieve happiness.</li>
<li>Practicing <a href="https://blog.davidtate.org/clear-and-present-leadership/">clear and present</a> leadership everyday I can (which is everyday).</li>
<li>Spending time with friends and loved ones.</li>
<li>Traveling more.</li>
<li>Working on projects that help me grow my technical acumen and skillset.</li>
<li>Giving back to my community (technical, city, or other ways).</li>
<li>Speaking up in the community, at start up events, or technical events.</li>
<li>Maintaining a healthy life &ndash; through daily walks, working out, and getting back to training jiu jitsu 3 times a week.</li>
</ul>


<p>Now, those are my systems. Based on those systems, I&rsquo;d like to achieve some goals:</p>

<ul>
<li>Have listened (audible) to 40 books this year.</li>
<li>Have read (physical or kindle) 40 books this year.</li>
<li>Have finished writing a book draft for my first book.</li>
<li>Writing at least 2 blog posts a month.</li>
<li>Have been present and aware as much as I could physically and mentally.</li>
<li>Practicing leadership with people I mentor or in the community.</li>
<li>Camped 10 different sites with friends and family.</li>
<li>Traveled to two countries this year.</li>
<li>Completed a meaningful project that helps people sell their used goods.</li>
<li>Given a talk at Ignite Boulder.</li>
<li>Have spoke at one technical conference.</li>
<li>Get back to a healthy 185lbs and be healhy enough to train jiu-jitsu 3 times a week consistently.</li>
</ul>


<p>I realize many of these goals seem binary, and thus, hard to measure. I will measure them by marking a calendar with the days that I achieve the above conditions. By the end of the year, I should see a high percentage of successes in the goals.</p>

<h1>Stop, Start, Continue</h1>

<p>I just read <a href="https://qbq.com/3-step-upgrade-how-to-become-a-better-me/">the QBQ 3-step upgrade post</a> about how to &lsquo;be a better me&rsquo;. I wanted to try out that exercise here.</p>

<h2>I will stop doing</h2>

<ul>
<li>Complaining about things unless I&rsquo;m willing to act on it.</li>
<li>Playing the victim card. I am taking full accountability.</li>
<li>Accusing other people for things that make me unhappy, I will make that my internal focus.</li>
<li>Doing things that do not bring me joy.</li>
<li>Masking my anger by using sarcasm.</li>
</ul>


<h2>I will start doing</h2>

<ul>
<li>Measuring what matters to me &ndash; my reading, my exercise, my habits.</li>
<li>Taking accountability for my actions.</li>
<li>Doing more self-care activities, like physical therapy, exercise, etc.</li>
<li>Doing more, talking less.</li>
<li>Living more by a budget.</li>
<li>Practicing randicle candor.</li>
<li>Reaching out to my parents on a daily/weekly cadence.</li>
</ul>


<h2>I will continue doing</h2>

<ul>
<li>Being kind whenever possible, it&rsquo;s always possible</li>
<li>Helping others when I can (the idea: in order to survive you, I must first survive myself)</li>
<li>Reaching out to others to give positive reinforcement.</li>
<li>Being a supportive son and brother to my family. Being a supportive person to my friends.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
