<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: mobile | Josh Bavari's Thoughts]]></title>
  <link href="http://jbavari.github.io/blog/categories/mobile/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jbavari.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2019-12-12T21:16:47-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://jbavari.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Josh Bavari]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[jbavari@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to be a good imitator in PhoneGap/Cordova]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbavari.github.io/blog/2014/03/11/how-to-be-a-good-imitator-in-phonegap-slash-cordova/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-11T01:02:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbavari.github.io/blog/2014/03/11/how-to-be-a-good-imitator-in-phonegap-slash-cordova</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you found your way here, then you&rsquo;re probably seeking knowlege about Phonegap/Cordova. I want to first remind you what the purpose of the PhoneGap / Cordova project is:</p>

<blockquote><p><a href="http://phonegap.com/2012/05/09/phonegap-beliefs-goals-and-philosophy/">The ultimate purpose of PhoneGap is to cease to exist.</a></p></blockquote>

<p>What this means is &ndash; you should really start getting ready to make Native-like apps regardless of what technology is used.</p>

<p>How can we give native apps a better feel from PhoneGap / Cordova? Or stated another way, what are some tricks we can use to make the application feel more native?</p>

<p>The answer then, is to be a better imitator, you must first understand what you are imitating.</p>

<h2>The chameleons change color to their surroundings</h2>

<p>Simply stated &ndash; you adapt to what your surroundings are.</p>

<p>Our surroundings for PhoneGap / Cordova are quite wide:</p>

<ul>
<li>iOS</li>
<li>Android</li>
<li>Windows Phone</li>
<li>BlackBerry</li>
<li>Firefox OS</li>
</ul>


<p>That is a lot to adapt to. It may take a little time to familiarize yourself with each platform. If you do though, your users will thank you.</p>

<h2>Some suggestions</h2>

<ul>
<li>Put navigation items near the top in Android, for iOS put them near the bottom. Users are used to having their navigation in the same place.</li>
<li>In Android / Windows Phone &ndash; mind the Back button! Users use their phones natively, and if you try to change this, they will hate your app.</li>
<li>Dont use the same button styles for each platform! Buttons on iOS do not look like buttons on Android &ndash; if you try this though, your users will notice and find it odd. <a href="http://goratchet.com/components/">See these great examples from Ratchet.js (look for the Base/iOS/Android buttons near the top)</a></li>
<li>Use Native-like loading animations. iOS generally has a small circle &ndash; if you try using this instead of your own custom loading icon, users will most likely blame their phone over your app. <a href="http://mercury.io/blog/the-psychology-of-waiting-loading-animations-and-facebook">See this study by Facebook for loading animations</a></li>
<li>Test on actual devices. You cant get a native feel from clicking on a simulator.</li>
</ul>


<p>References:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.tricedesigns.com/2013/03/11/performance-ux-considerations-for-successful-phonegap-apps/">Performance UX Considerations for successful PhoneGap apps</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.mikedellanoce.com/2012/09/10-tips-for-getting-that-native-ios.html">Tips for getting that native feel</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
